<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe description of the reasons that make the declaration of the ban made against the King of Bohemia, as being Elector Palatine, dated the 22. of Ianuarie last past, of no value nor worth, and therefore not to be respected</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11353</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118722</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853929</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853929</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19332</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01240)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19332)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1097:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe description of the reasons that make the declaration of the ban made against the King of Bohemia, as being Elector Palatine, dated the 22. of Ianuarie last past, of no value nor worth, and therefore not to be respected</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Arnold Meuris bookeseller at the signe of the Bible [i.e. by E. Allde for T. Archer?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at the Hayf [sic, i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The imprint is false. Actual place of publication and suggested printer and publisher from STC.</note>
                  <note>On 13 August 1621 Allde and Archer were ordered to be imprisoned for printing this--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Frederick --  I, --  King of Bohemia, 1596-1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  1618-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19332:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19332:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Briefe Deſcription of the reaſons that make the Declaration of the Ban made againſt the King of <hi>Bohemia, as being Elector Palatine, Dated the</hi> 22. of Ianuarie laſt paſt, of no value nor worth; and therefore not to be reſpected.</p>
            <p>PRINTED At the Hayf by <hi>Arnold Meuris</hi> Booke-ſeller, at the Signe of the Bible. 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19332:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19332:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE DESRIPTION OF THE REASONS THAT MAKE the declaration of the Ban, made againſt the King of Bohemia, as being Elector Palatine. Dated the 22. of Ianuarie laſt paſt, of no value <hi>nor worth, and therefore not to be reſpected.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, in that pretended proces, there is found a moſt great imperfection in the principall foundation and ground there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. That is touching the matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of the Imperiall iuriſdiction: for that neither Diuine, naturall, nor ciuill Law, doth permit the Emperour to be Iudge in his owne cauſe, or that hee can, in the preſent difference now made, wherein there is a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on touching a pretended vſurpation of the Crowne of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, and of the intereſt of the houſe of Auſtria, ground the afore-ſaid Declaration, vpon a breach of publike peace, and conſequently in the purſute of his particular intereſt, to ſerue his turne againſt his aduerſe party, with moſt rigorous penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the conſtitutions of the ſaid Peace, which conſiſt in the loſſe of all his Goods, Countries, honours, &amp; namely his life.</p>
            <p>For although men wil not diſpute nor ſtriue with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror touching the power that he hath, by vertue of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions aforeſaid of the Empire, againſt the breakers of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19332:3"/> publike peace, which according to the opinion of ciuil Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, a Iudge may iudge of, and make Decrees concerning his Office, and iudiciall authority, as alſo touching the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation thereof: yet it is moſt certaine and euident, as well by the Iudgements of all Ciuill Lawyers, as by naturall equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that the maxime aforeſaid, is graunted onely in caſes, wherein there is no queſtion made of an intereſt, profit, and great aduantage of the Iudge, and when the Act in it ſelfe is moſt manifeſt, and without any doubt or difficulty whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. Otherwiſe, and for want of ſuch circumſtances, it is moſt dangerous, that one ſelfe ſame perſon ſhould be Iudge and party, or that the Iudge and the party ſhould ſit both in one ſeate: for it ſhall be ſhewed, and moſt euidently decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hereafter, that in this pretended Declaration, there is no reſpect had vnto the ſaid common doctrine of the Law, nor to naturall equity. Beſides, that the golden Bull, as a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall law of the Empire, in expreſſe termes moſt plainely abſolueth this queſtion. That is, whether the Emperour may or can be Iudge, in that which concernes his particular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, or thoſe of his houſe, ſaying: That an Emperour, as King of Romanes, in cauſes and matters that are alledged againſt him, is bound by an auncient cuſtome, to appeare and anſwere before the Elector Palatine, as not being permitted to be Iudge in his owne cauſe. Which words, ſo cleare, and ſo expreſſe, ſhould be vnprofitable, and of no effect, if an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of Rome could be both Iudge and party. And ſuch an abſolute power of the Emperour, was neuer at any time heard of, nor knowne among; nor vnto the true &amp; good Almaines or Germaines, as being directly contrary to their liberties: and it will be found, namely in the time of <hi>Frederick</hi> the third, in the controuerſies betweene Duke <hi>Albert</hi> and his brother, as alſo in the differences of <hi>Habsburg:</hi> yea, and by ſome exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the houſe of Auſtria it ſelfe, that ordinance of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19332:3"/> golden Bull, and fundamentall conſtitution of the Empire, was confirmed by a conſequent obſeruation. Conſidering that the precedent Emperours of moſt worthy memory, did alwayes ſubmit themſelues to the ordinary courſe of Law, at all times when any queſtion was to be decided touching their particular patrimoniall goods and poſſeſſions: So farre off were they from ſuffering themſelues to bee caried away to ſuch a paſſion and rigour in their owne intereſts and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, as in this caſe, which at this time is in queſtion, Such kinde of violence being not exerciſed in an other mans cauſe, of much greater conſequence, which concerned the loſſe of diuers Prouinces and notable Townes, withdrawne from the obedience of the Empire, the forces and reuenewes whereof are weakened and diminiſhed more then the halfe.</p>
            <p>Further, and ſecondly, it cannot be denied, That the caſe in queſtion, doth not particularly touch nor concerne, (nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the firſt and higheſt degree) the Emperor &amp; his houſe: and yet notwithſtanding, the pretended Declaration, hath beene decreed, and concluded by his Counſellours, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, who by a moſt ſtrict Oath; (whereof there is no releaſe in this point) are bound to procure the good of their Maſter. And for that the ſaid Counſellours and ſeruants, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the troubles of Bohemia, haue ſufficiently ſhewed, that their intents, and preiudicate Iudgements, proceede from a hatred and a moſt extraordinary animoſetie, not only againſt the reformed Religion, and thoſe that generally make profeſſion thereof, but alſo againſt the perſon of the King of Bohemia, and the Elector Palatine, particularly. In this, that in all, and in euery place they haue ſought to condemne him, before they heard him ſpeake for himſelfe, or once receiued his Iuſtifications. It is eaſily to be iudged that this pretended Ban, the Declaration whereof was conſulted of, drawne and publiſhed by the wills and conſents of the Emperiall ſeruants
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19332:4"/> aforeſaid, had no reaſon, nor any ground of impartiall Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and that conſequently all the Proces is of no force nor value, paſſion and animoſetie (as it is ſaid) hauing therein had all the gouernment &amp; direction, treading Iuſtice vnder foot.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, in this point it is to be noted &amp; well waighed, what men may iudge &amp; eſteeme of all the points of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, which without all reaſon and nature it ſelfe, was begun and intimated by the execution. In this that Marquis <hi>Spinola,</hi> vnder the pretence of an Imperiall Commiſſion, with his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie raiſed and payed by the King of Spaine, did by manner of hoſtility inuade the Electorall Palatinate, before the ſaid pretended Declaration of the Ban was publiſhed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, there was no manner of reſpect had of any of the States and Countries that were neutrall, and therefore wholy inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: as it appeareth manifeſtly by the ruine and intire deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of that ſo flouriſhing a Country, which iuſtly might be compared with the beſt parts of Germanie, which is directly contrary to the Emperiall capitulation: by vertue whereof, no Emperour is permitted, to vſe any ſuch violence: but by a moſt ſingular wiſedome and fore-ſight it was referred to the lawes and faſhions of the Warres vſed amongſt the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Germanes, and reduced to certaine termes in ſuch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the members of the Empire, in theſe words. That the Empire ſhall not forcibly aſſaile the Electors, Princes, and other States of the Empire, but hauing any queſtion or controuerſie againſt any of them, to ſhun and auoid all vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, troubles, and commotions, hee ſhall cauſe the ſame to be deſcided by way of Iuſtice, and ſhall not permit them, to be vexed, nor purſued by armes, violences, or inuaſions. For if in caſe of leſſe conſequence, a Iudge, before Iudgement giuen, proceding by actuall force againſt a party, loſeth all his credit, and is deputed of the authority and power of a Iudge, as it is moſt true: what may be ſaid of him, that ſetteth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19332:4"/> vpon his aduerſe party by open force and armes, diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him of all his goods and eſtates, and at the end of all his violences and indirect and wicked proceedings, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him guilty, and proclaimeth the Imperiall Ban againſt him.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing, that for the fourth reaſon, in all formalitie of Iuſtice, ſpecially in that which concerneth a publike vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and outrage, it is neceſſarie, that the leaſt and meaneſt peſant or Citizen that is accuſed, ought to be orderly ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned, to yeeld a reaſon of his actions: by greater reaſon, it is moſt neceſſarie and conuenient, that this requiſite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality ſhould be obſerued towards an Elector of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, of ſo high a houſe, and ſo great a dignity, as the Elector Palatine, ſpecially when it concernes his goods, his eſtate, his Country, his life, and his honor; and to be ſhort, all that which he poſſeſſeth in this world: For ſpecially to ſpeake of the crime of the infraction and perturbation of the publike peace, it appeareth by the lawes of the Empire, that before all things; the party, that is to be accuſed of ſuch a crime, ſhould be ſummoned, and heard in his iuſtifications, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, that after an exact vnderſtanding of the fact, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may the better be giuen, and knowledge had whether the publike peace and tranquility hath bin violated and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. And to that end, that the party may not be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſubmitted to the moſt rigorous paines of the Ban, at the only requeſt, or vnder a falſe ſuggeſtion of the contrary partie: which can not be iuſtified, neither by the ordinances of the Imperiall chamber, made and concluded in forme of a publike and perpetuall contract betweene the head and the members of the Empire, nor alſo by the capitulation; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, as the precedent Emperors, ſo alſo the Emperor at this day bound himſelfe by a ſolemne Oath: within expreſſe and manifeſt tearmes ſaith. That his Maieſtie ſhall not permit,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19332:5"/> that from henceforth, any of the ſtates of the Empire, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector, Prince, or others, ſhall be put into the Imperiall Ban, without cauſe, and without lawfull knowledge of the ſame: but that in ſuch caſe, hee ſhall obſerue the formalities, and lawfull proceedings, all in conformity of the conſtitutions and cuſtomes of the Empire, according to the tenor of the reformed ordinances of the Chamber, and Soueraigne Court, publiſhed touching the ſame. Now although all this is moſt true &amp; manifeſt, yet it hath all bin put out of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; of the tenor of the pretended declaration: ſeeing that without citation, without knowledge of the cauſe, without any formalitie, they haue gon ſo farre as in their own proper cauſe, to proceed to a moſt manifeſt iniuſt ſentence, and to declare an Elector of the Empire to be a criminall: who by the golden Bull, is qualified to be one of the principall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body, and a pillar of the Empire: whoſe electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dignity in the Empire, is eſteemed to be of no leſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count then the Royall. To whom for an accompliſhment of all iniquity; they deny that which is due to the moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and greateſt malefactors, yea and to the wicked ſpirits themſelues, (as ſome men ſay) who are not condemned, without their cauſe be firſt heard: ſeeing that it is altogether manifeſt, that this pretended ſentence againſt the King of Bohemia, was not onely publiſhed without any formalitie, as it hath many times bin ſayd, but extorted and procured by the importunate ſolicitations of the Spaniſh Ambaſſador, at whoſe lodging the firſt counſell was holden, as alſo by trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties made vnder hand and cauteouſly with the Archbiſhop of <hi>Mayence</hi> and others, all without the knowledge of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall colledge: which ought lawfully to aſſemble, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murely to waigh the pernicious conſequence of ſo violent and rigorous a proceeding, whereof may enſue the ruine and entire deſolation of all the Countrie.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19332:5"/>
            <p>And although they ſeeke to colour and excuſe this head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong proceeding (which is ſo much the better knowne, that tenne monthes before the pretended ſentence, they beganne to practiſe the execution by force of armes) in this ſort, that by vertue of the Emperiall conſtitutions and edicts, in caſe of a manifeſt and permanent rebellion, there is no neede of any formall Proces againſt thoſe that are attainted, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the tenor of the ſame it is permitted to proceed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually (againſt thoſe that are culpable) by force of armes: and yet they cannot ſhew any ſuch manifeſtation of the Act which is now in queſtion. Seeing that the King of Bohemia, did neither by practiſes, force, or other meanes, intrude himſelfe into the Kingdome, but entred therein, and tooke poſſeſſion by a moſt iuſt Title, as beleeuing moſt aſſuredly that the Crowne was vacant, as appeareth by the manifeſt proteſtations and declarations by him publiſhed and ſent into all the parts of <hi>Europe.</hi> In ſuch manner, that the notice required, to forme a Proceſſe vpon the conſtitutions, againſt the perturbators of the publike peace, can haue no place in this ſubiect; and if this pretended infraction be ſo notorious as they ſayd, why did they not at the firſt ſerue their turnes, with the reaſons and edicts of the Empire, which they now alledge? Why did they deferre eight moneths, and vntill the aſſembly at <hi>Mulhauſen,</hi> (whereof there could not a copie be had, notwithſtanding all the inſtance that could be vſed therein) to frame a Proces in ſo notorious a crime as they pretend it to be? why did they not in an Act holden to be ſo euident, ſtand to the conſtitutions publiſhed for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Emperiall Ban? why did they not call the iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions to put their helping hands therevnto? But why in a crime made ſo notorious, did a great part of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Romaine ſtates declare themſelues Neutrall? Why were they prayed and requeſted as well by the Emperor, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19332:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> by the Arch Duke <hi>Albertus</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and Marquis <hi>Spinola,</hi> to continue and abide in thoſe tearmes of Neutralitie? ſeeing it is ſo, that in ſuch and the like actions concerning the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like neceſſitie of the Countrie, euery one is bound, to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute ſomething thereunto; and without any exemption, to aide and ſuccour thoſe, that therein are oppreſſed? And how comes it, that the Duke of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uiere,</hi> with his Armie intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Emperiall commiſſion, maketh a diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Elector Palatine, and the ſtates of Bohemia, whom hee ſaith hee would purſue as notorious rebells. A crime whereof he diſchargeth the Elector Palatine, when he ſaith, that touching him, the ſayd Elector, hee ſtood not in ſuch tearmes: And beſides all theſe things, this pretended notoriouſnes is made voide and diſanulled, by the diuers deductions and apologies of the ſayd edicts of the Realme of Bohemia, which are extant through out the world.</p>
            <p>We muſt no leſſe conſider for the firſt point, that in this exorbitance, they ſeeke to ground the pretended declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Emperiall Ban, onely vpon the Emperiall conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Empire, touching the publike peace, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe; according to the tenor thereof, doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne nor bind the King of Bohemia, ſeeing that ſuch conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, were not made nor determined within, but with the ſixe Electors, and other ſtates of the Empire, concerning the ſuperiors, and the ſubiects, comprehended in the tenne iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of Germainy: and that ſo a ſtate of the Empire can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be puniſhed nor perſecuted as a breaker of the publike peace, by reaſon of an offence imputed to the King of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, for it is moſt euident and manifeſt, that a King of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, doth not acknowledge the ſuperioritie of a Romaine Emperor, but in regard of the Electorall dignitie, and of the Office of chiefe Cupbearer; and that touching other things, the Crowne of Bohemia is exempted from his Emperiall iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19332:6"/> in the ſame manner that diuers other vaſſals and members of the Empire are, as Milan, Sanoye, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in Italie and elſe where: which neither will be, nor are bound to the aforeſayd conſtitutions, touching the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of publike peace: from whence alſo it follow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h that in the Emperiall aſſemblies, and when queſtion is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de of contributions for monies, and other affaires: the ſayd Realme is alwaies accounted as a ſtranger, and is not bound to contribute to the charges of the executions of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, againſt the publike perterbators thereof: as it is yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by the declaration made by the Emperor <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the firſt, to the ſtates of the Empire, <hi>Anno</hi> 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wherein hee proteſteth and ſaith, that the ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Realme of Bohemia is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted, and dependeth not on the Empire. And the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is yet freſh touching that which hapned to the Emperor <hi>Rodulph,</hi> for whoſe ſake no man ſtirred, although his two Crownes were taken from him, and that hee had held the Scepter, and gouerned the Empire 36. yeares. And it was neuer vnderſtood that the Crowne of Bohemia, had any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect or regard to the publike tranquilitie of the Empire, or to the publike lawes for the conſeruation thereof, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes followed the example of other Realmes, and ſtrange Potentates, according to their lawes and perticular cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes.</p>
            <p>But looking neerer into the conſtitutions concerning the publike peace, as the onely ground and foundation alledged by this declaration; we ſhall cleerely by the qualities that therein are required, perceiue and ſee the nullitie thereof: for as in all faults and offences a man muſt be attainted of a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt practiſe to make him culpable: ſo in this crime of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the publike peace, the like muſt be done. Now tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the King of Bohemia, whom they will make criminall in this ſubiect, it will neuer be proued, that he did euer vſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19332:7"/> any practiſe or fraud, neither before the acceptation of the Crowne of Bohemia, at the receiuing thereof, nor after the ſame: for thoſe that haue publiſhed the declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therin at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, that preſently after the troubles raiſed in the ſame realm; his Maieſtie vſed all the meanes he could to quench that fire, and to end that difference: from whence he ſolemnely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth, calling and taking God to witnes, that he neuer practiſed to haue that election put vpon him, which ſo vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly fell vnto him: which aſſertions and aſſurances hee may well ſtand vpon, vntill ſuch time that the contrarie is ſhewed and brought to light, which vntill this day neuer any man duſt vndertake. In ſuch manner, that it cannot be ſuppoſed, that his Maieſty euer had any deſſeigne or thought to breake and trouble the publike peace: becauſe he alwayes alledged the ſayd Title to be lawfull, wherewith the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror would ſerue his turne in his pretences. And put the caſe, that in the refuſall of the ſayd Emperor, the ſtate, of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia did commit a fault (which yet is not proued) that neuer the leſſe cannot be imputed to a practiſe or deceite in the King of Bohemia: He hauing not in any ſort done, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured any thing to that effect; much leſſe then ought they to vſe any extreamities againſt him either in his body, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, or goods, before he were conuicted of deceit and frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent dealing.</p>
            <p>For touching that which they alledge; that he, as he is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector Palatine is bound to beare reſpect vnto the Emperor, that cannot in any manner iuſtifie theſe proceedings; for that he hath alway borne that reſpect vnto the Emperor, that is due vnto him as Emperor, and neuer pretended any thing againſt him in that qualitie; but onely in qualitie of Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke of Auſtria: He hath not alſo enterpriſed any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his greatnes and Imperiall authoritie. And it cannot be verified by the Oath of fidelitie of the Princes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19332:7"/> that any mention is therin made touching the goods &amp; Patrimoniall eſtates of the houſe of Auſtria. In ſuch manner that in theſe occurrents of Bohemia, touching the perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar pretences of the ſayd houſe of Auſtria; that Oath of fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie will ſerue their turnes as litle as it did when the ſtates of the Empire did by vertue of the ſayd Oath, refuſe to deale with the warres which the Emperor <hi>Maximilian</hi> the firſt had with Fraunce, the Venetians, the Low-countries, and Zwit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland; or to take part with the quarrell of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, againſt <hi>William</hi> Duke of Iulliers in reſpect of Gelderland, or to eſteeme that the recouerie of the Dutchie of Wertem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg was a thing that concerned the Empire, or that it was a matter of high treaſon. Likewiſe it is an allegation of no force, to alledge the reuolt made in Auſtria, by meanes of the Bohemian armie, to proue the practiſe and deceite alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; ſeeing it is manifeſt, that the ſame Armie was vnder the pay and commaund of the ſayd ſtates of Bohemia, and ſent by them into Auſtria, thereby to diuert their enemies, and to recouer that good &amp; treaſure which the Earle of Dampiere had forcibly taken from them in their Countrie, and that a good while before the Election, and acceptation of the Crowne of Bohemia, in ſuch manner that the ſame reuolt, cannot be imputed to the King of Bohemia.</p>
            <p>Now, for that by vertue of the ſaid moſt manifeſt diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſet downe in the conſtitution of the Empire, <hi>anno</hi> 1594. it is neceſſary, that in all actions, whereon men will ground the rigorous paines and puniſhments, pronounced againſt the infringers of publike peace, the qualities thereof ought to be euidently ſhewed, together with a manifeſt proofe of a true (and not a faigned) indirect courſe, and that for want thereof, the defendant and he that is accuſed ought neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to be abſolued. Seeing alſo, that the Elector Palatine hath etterprized nothing but that; whereunto, the generall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19332:8"/> election of fiue ſeuerall Prouinces had inuited him: and that after the example of diuers other Potentates, and namely of thoſe of the houſe of Auſtria, to diſcharge his conſcience, and to preſerue the ſaid Prouinces from greater deſolation and danger, to be wholy withdrawne from the Empire, wherein he hath been more commended then blamed by diuers great perſonages and others, namely Strangers, hauing a regard to the State of the affaires, the Bohemians griefes, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire whereinto they were reduced. Therefore it is referred to the Iudgement of all the world; whether his actions ought to be held and iudged to be a rupture of the publicke peace, And whether in regard of the ſame, a moſt notable and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall member of the Empire, without notice of the cauſe, and againſt the conſtitutions and capitulations aforeſaid, ought to be baniſhed and dealt withall in ſuch manner: with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dement to all others, not to adhere vnto him, nor yet in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy manner to ayde him (although it ſhould be only againſt the ſence of the ſaid Declaration of Ban) vpon paine of loſſe of life, and likewiſe to be comprehended in the ſaid Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: which is no other but to introduce a Spaniſh ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and to attribute vnto the Emperour, an abſolute au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of life and death ouer all the States of the Empire, that would oppoſe themſelues againſt the particular pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of ſucceſſion, and others of his houſe. Whereby it would follow, that the Emperour ſhould be permitted to ſerue his turne, (by the meanes of his paſſionate Counſellors) with an abſolute power, which the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> call <hi>plenitudinem pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis,</hi> as in effect in the ſaid Declaration, more then once they preſuppoſe ſuch a power, for the ground thereof: although the capitulation made with an Oath by the Emperour to the Electors, ſhould derogate from an abſolute power, and that the Doctors of the Ciuill Law will not heare, ſpeaking of an Act of ſo great importance; and ſo the Emperour (by vertue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19332:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> of that power, without any contradiction) might decree, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, and doe what he thought good for his particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, or for that of his friends, or to the preiudice of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Germanie, notwithſtanding all Emperiall conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ordinances.</p>
            <p>To conclude, all true Germanes and louers of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and the Liberties of the ſame, are deſired and coniured to haue a regard to this lo ſuddaine, extraordinary, and moſt dangerous proceeding to all the States of both Religions, and to beleeue, <hi>Quod cuiuis contingere poteſt quod cuiquam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingit.</hi> The moſt puiſſant God, direct and guide the thoughts of euery man in the way of truth and equity, and of his paternall grace, cauſe our natiue and deere Countrey, to enioy a good and ſecure peace.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
